ANS Record Group 2: Curatorial, 1858-ongoing
American Numismatic Society
- Series 10: George C. Miles curator correspondence, research materials, and lectures, 1933 - 1974; 3 cubic feet (4 boxes)
  - Box 1 of 5 - Correspondence
    - Bruckner, Geraldine (University Museum, University of Pennsylvania)
    - Brunner, Christopher
    - Burn, Richard (Sir)
    - Caley, Earle R.
    - Coolidge, John (Fogg Art Museum)
    - Cora collection
    - Curiel, Raoul
    - DeShazo, A. S.
    - Dols, Michael
    - Encyclopedia Persica
    - Erdmann, Kurt
    - Ettinghausen, Richard F.
    - Fahmy, Abd al-Rahman.
    - Farrugia de Candia, M. J.
    - Faure, Paul
    - Fitzwilliam Museum
    - Freeman, Sarah
    - Frye, Richard G.
    - Garcia-Gomez, E.
    - Ghirshman, Roman
    - Gibb, H. A. R.
    - Goodrich, L. Carrington
    - Glidden, Harold W.
    - Göbl, Robert
    - Grabar, Oleg
    - Grierson, Philip
    - Gropp, G.
    - Grohmann, Adolf
    - Gurnet, Robert
    - Jungfleisch, M.
    - Lane-Poole, Austin
    - Leuthold, Enrique
    - Levi Della Vida, G.
    - Levy, S.
    - Lopez, R. S.
    - Luther, Kenneth A.M.
    - Mackenzie, Franklin
    - Mateu y Llopis, Philipe
    - Morton, A. H.
    - Mottahedeh, Roy P.
    - Murraciole, P.
    - Moutsopoulos, N. C.
    - Marinho, Jose R.
    - Minorsky, V.
    - Madelung, Wilfred
    - Morris, Robert W.
    - Nahapetian, Yervand
    - Pereire, Roger
    - Poladian, Armenak
    - Schmidt, Erich
    - Walker, John
    - Assorted
  - Box 2 of 5 - Lectures and Photographs
      nnan0115/c_c35de8d039613b1469bfa1523f8066ae
    - Lecture outlines, 1959-1964
    - Lectures, 1952
    - Lectures, 1952-1956
    - Lectures, 1953-1954
    - Lectures, 1959
    - Lecture: Islamic numismatics, 1946
    - Lecture: Archaeology – Millbrook School, 1952
    - Lecture: Numismatic crossroad, 1952
    - Lecture: Numismatics as a field of study, 1955
    - Lecture: Crete, 1956-1971
    - Lecture: The role of coins in history, 1957
    - Lecture: Arabs in Greece?, 1959
    - Lecture: Islam and Byzantium, a numismatic commentary, 1959 (revised 1961 and 1965)
    - Lectures: Byzantines and Arabs, 1963
    - Lecture: The role of numismatics in archaeology, 1963-1965
    - Lecture: St. Paul’s Travels
    - Lecture: Traces of the Arabs in Greece, 1965
    - Lecture: A bird’s-eye view of Greek coins, 1972
    - Lecture: Survival of Sasonian motifs, 1973
    - Photographs: Abu Sa’id coin
    - Photographs: Egyptian weights (1 of 2)
    - Photographs: Egyptian weights (2 of 2)
    - Photographs: pasted plates of A Catalog of the Palace Collection of Ancient Coins and Bronzes by Imperial Order, Shizheng, et al.
  - Box 3 of 5 - Research Materials
      nnan0115/c_b3b1ea475ea0d2f6893d6fa970117323
    - “Numismatica Hispanica” [Hispanic numismatic series?] proposal.
    - Abdullah
    - Abbasid Partisan
    - Ahnas/Misr
    - Ali b. Isa
    - Arabs in Crete – Arabic Sources
    - Arab Imitations of Byzantine AE of Alexandria
    - Arab Sasanians, New
    - Armenian Gold Ring
    - A------- hoard
    - Atabeg coins – Photos
    - Atabeg coins – Prototypes
    - Behbud
    - Dirham
    - Dirhem hoard
    - Dune hoard – Stockholm
    - Dirhems, Oversized – Now ANS
    - Dulafids, Abu
    - Egyptian Damqhas – Hall-marks
    - Earliest Arab gold coinage
    - Early Arab Dinars
    - Ghayunavid hoard
    - Istakhr – tables
    - Istakhr – photographs
    - Islamic numismatics
    - Kakwayhid hoard
    - Kakwayhids
    - Kekova coins
    - Kevorkian collection
    - Kharijite dirham – ‘Ubaydah al-Taghlibi
    - Lead seals
    - Masabadhan
    - Mihrab, ‘Anazah and ‘Alam (paper read at AOS in 1949, plus research notes)
    - Misr mint – rare Abbasids
    - Mousa Settareh hoard
    - Muzaffarids
    - Nishapur
    - Normans of Sicily
    - Persepolis - NR
    - Persepolis – Islamic inscriptions
    - Persepolis - Tall-i-Bakun
    - Rayy – Luristan notes, 1934
    - Rayy – Luristan miscellaneous correspondence
    - Rayy – numismatics, 1934-1936
    - Rayy – 1934-1936
    - Rayy – Oriental Institute
    - Rayy – Parthian hoard
    - Rayy – miscellaneous notes
    - Salgharid medallion
    - Samarra mint
    - Sasanian metrology
    - Seljuq coins in the ANS
    - Shahs of Persia
    - Counterstamped Turkish AE
    - Turkoman Song
    - Unpublished early tombstones
    - Ziyarids
    - Assorted
    - Binder: History of the Crusades, correspondence, including of Michael Bates, 1970s, 1980s
  - Box 4 of 5 - Index card set
      nnan0115/c_618ab280768b3d4f018726eac3fa1203
    - Rayy history and names of persons
  - Box 5 of 5 - Index card set
      nnan0115/c_ce98195718ecfaf17f0e071ae3af1acb
    - Visigoths
- Series 11: Henry Grunthal curator correspondence, 1967-1969; 2 cubic feet (2 boxes)
  Rubbings (Visual works); Correspondence; Grunthal, Henry, 1905-2001
  Contains official correspondence from Grunthal's work as curator at the American Numismatic Society, primarily letters between Grunthal and his colleagues and members of the American Numismatic Society (ANS), coin collectors, and the general public about the cost and historical values of coins, medals, and paper money. The letters also include queries about the identification of coins and potential acquisitions, visits to the ANS, and the recommendation of dealers. Some queries were passed along to the ANS from other organizations, such as universities and galleries. Answers to queries include identification summaries, estimated values, and sources to consult. The collection includes both the letter received and the letter sent and occasionally coin rubbings. Letters are from all over the world, including Hong Kong, Canada, Tasmania, West Bengal India, Toronto, Singapore, Malaysia, Nicaragua, Uganda, England and Italy.
  Henry Grunthal (1905-2001) of the Riverdale section of the Bronx in New York City was born in Cologne, Germany, and was the son of numismatist and medal publisher Hugo Grunthal. He joined the American Numismatic Society (ANS) staff in 1953 as assistant to the chief curator and moved up to the position of curator of European and modern coins, a position he held until his retirement in 1973. His main activities at the ANS were building, labeling, and organizing the collections and assisting members with the identification and appraisal of coins, paper money, and medals. He was educated at the Friedrich Wilhelm University in Berlin, the University of Jena, and at the Sorbonne in Paris, where he studied archaeology and art history. He also studied numismatics under Kurt Regling in Berlin and Geheimrat Pick in Gotha. In 1938 he emigrated to the United States from Germany to work for Stack's Rare Coins in New York City. After retirement he was an independent numismatic consultant in New York City, where he also conducted auctions with Edward Gans at Numismatic Fine Arts. He wrote several articles for publications such as The Numismatist and Coin World and co-authored two books, Carolingian Coinage and The Coinage of Peru. He was awarded the American Numismatic Association Medal of Merit in 1970. Grunthal also received an ANS medal marking fifty years of continuous membership in 1979. He had been a member of the American Numismatic Association since 1929 and was active in both the Bronx Coin Club and the New York Numismatic Club, both of which he served as president.
    nnan0115/c_362188d77e624b85440fdf2293fcd871
  - Box 1 of 2: 1967-1968
  - Box 2 of 2: 1969
- Series 12: Michael L. Bates curator correspondence and coin photographs, 1958-2004; 5 cubic feet (5 boxes)
  Some files are in alphabetical order; others are chronologically arranged.
  Correspondence; Invitations; Announcements; Floor plans; Bates, Michael L., 1941-; Miles, George Carpenter, 1904-1975
  Michael L. Bates was born in Louisville, Kentucky, in 1941. He obtained bachelor (1963) and doctorate (1975) degrees from the University of Chicago, with his education and research culminating in his dissertation, Yemen and Its Conquest by the Ayyubids of Egypt (A.D. 1137-1202). He served as assistant curator (1970-1972), associate curator (1972-1977), and curator of Islamic coins (1977-2004), with his thirty-four year term of service as an ANS curator being the longest in the Society’s history. A major undertaking of Bates’s early years at ANS was the sorting and attributing of what were believed to be nearly 2,000 thirteenth-century Ayyubid silver dirhams, a hoard the ANS purchased in 1971, with nearly a third of the coins found to be Crusader imitations. Bates then turned his attention to studying coins of the Umayyad caliphate (661-750), and was granted a National Endowment for the Arts fellowship to travel to England and France to further study them. In 1978, 1980, and 1982-1983, he served as a coin expert at the American excavations at Fustat, the oldest Islamic section of Cairo. He was first elected a member of the International Numismatic Commission (INC) in 1979, and in addition to publishing on a variety of topics, Bates also organized educational seminars at ANS on topics such as collecting Islamic coins and the Arab-Sasanian coinage of Iran.
- Series 13: Jeremiah D. Brady curator correspondence, 1916 - 1981; 0.7 cubic feet (2 boxes)
  Correspondence; Photographs; Brady, Jeremiah, 1940-; Ebsen, Buddy, 1908-2003; Goetz, Karl, 1875-1950; O'Sullivan, Frank; Appleton, Arthur; Eliscu, Frank, 1912-1996
  Jeremiah Brady (b. 1940), originally of Fall River, Massachusetts, obtained a bachelor’s degree from Harvard College (1961), an M.Litt. from Cambridge University (1963), and a Ph.D. in medieval history from Harvard (1972). He served as assistant (1970) then associate (1972) curator of medieval coins at ANS until 1980, when he left to take a position with Sotheby Parke-Bernet. During his years with the ANS, Brady was responsible for numerous projects in addition to his normal curatorial work, including the mounting the exhibit “Coinage of the Americas” for the 1973 International Numismatic Congress, coordinating the commissioning of the 1977 ANS members medal, and authoring Sylloge of Coins of the British Isles.
  Appears to be mostly materials relating to his position as secretary of the ANS standing committee on medals (1973-1976) and medals and decorations (1977-1980). There are correspondence, photographs, and other items having to do with a competition for a new design for a member’s medal in 1977, including photographs of plaster models and design critiques by committee and jury members of Frank Eliscu’s winning design. Also present are materials relating to additions to the Society’s collection of medals by Karl Goetz, such as a donation by Christian “Buddy” Ebson (1979) and correspondence on Goetz’s Lusitania medal, which includes the earliest item in the series, a J. Schulman invoice listing a Goetz medal (1916); correspondence relating to a legal matter arising over the attribution of a possibly imitation Davis Guard medal commemorating the Civil War battle of Sabine Pass (1974-1975); and files on donations from Frank O’Sullivan (1979.60) and Arthur Appleton (1978.64). There are three notebooks of materials (1976-1979) relating to a project relating to the documentation of all medals issued by the ANS since its founding in 1858. The notebooks contain completed forms with information on the medals, some correspondence, and photocopies from published sources as well as circulars (fliers) for some of the medals, such as Ernest Babelon (1912), Declaration of War (1917), and Catskill Aqueduct (1917), Prince of Wales (1919), and Centennial (1958).
    nnan0115/c_3067ebdb8f607d717bd5f70a82c26fbb
  - Box 2 of 2
      nnan0115/c_6379df1b8a1a008c36b02b6b6046f4d1
    - Three notebooks on ANS medals
- Series 14: Nancy M. Waggoner curator correspondence and other material, 1968-1989; 1.5 cubic feet (2 boxes)
  Waggoner, Nancy M., 1924-1989; Gans, Edward, 1887-1991; Mirza, H.H; Kelley, Robert F., 1894-1976; Lindren, Henry; Correspondence; Notes; Lectures
  Nancy M. Waggoner (1924-1989) graduated from Smith College (B.A., 1946) before attending Columbia University (M.A., 1963; Ph.D., 1968), where she studied under Margaret Thompson in the first seminar in numismatics, which ultimately resulted in her dissertation on the mint of Alexander the Great at Babylon. She served ANS as assistant curator (1968) and curator (1976) of Greek Coins and took over the Columbia seminar when Margaret Thompson retired in 1979. She remained at ANS until her retirement in 1988 and died the following year. After her death, the ANS held a symposium in her honor, which resulted in the publication in 1991 of Mnemata: Papers in Memory of Nancy M. Waggoner. Her two major publications were: Archaic Greek Silver Coinage. The “Asyut” Hoard, which she co-authored with Martin Price, and Early Greek Coins in the Collection of Jonathan P. Rosen, a volume in the Society’s ACNAC (American Coins in North American Collections) series. In addition, Waggoner supervised the publication of three volumes of the Society’s contribution to the Sylloge Nummorum Graecorum.
  Contains correspondence (1981-1988) on a variety of topics relating to her work as curator of Greek coins at the American Numismatic Society, including letters mostly with other scholars, but also with the general public, discussing the study of coins and their identification, attribution, and sometimes value, occasionally with coin photographs included. Also present are letters of recommendation and introduction written for others; correspondence and other materials relating to the development of ANS collections, such as an appraisal and articles relating to the Robert F. Kelley bequest (1977) and letters relating to the possible availability of coins from the H.H. Mirza (1983) and Henry Lindren (1984) collections; a report, procedures, and other materials having to do with the ANS photo file (photofile) (1980); a letter from Edward Gans on the history of his collecting and how he “abandoned the collecting of coins,” having lost his wife and his vision (1985); an agreement form concerning materials from Athos Moretti on temporary deposit at ANS (1986); notes, research letters, and materials relating to her efforts in 1974 to build upon her 1968 dissertation on a die-study of the Alexander mint at Babylon; and session lectures and student papers from the seminar she taught at Columbia University (1982-1989).
- Series 15: Alan M. Stahl curator correspondence and other material, 1914-2000, bulk 1982-2000; 13 cubic feet (13 boxes)
  Though some patterns can be discerned, the materials are unarranged. This disorder may have been the result of the packing and unpacking of the records during one of the Society’s physical relocations that took place after Stahl’s departure.
  Jovine, Marcel, 1921-2003; Brenner, Victor D. (Victor David), 1871-1924; Morgan, J. P. (John Pierpont), 1867-1943; Jovine, Marcel, 1921-2003; Correspondence; Notes; Memorandums; Photographs; Designs (Concepts); Fédération internationale de la médaille; American Medallic Sculpture Association
  Alan M. Stahl (b. 1947) of Ossining, N.Y., was curator of medieval coins and of medals at the American Numismatic Society from 1980 to 2000. Born in Providence, Rhode Island, Stahl graduated from the University of California at Berkeley (B.A., 1968) and the University of Pennsylvania (M.A., 1973; Ph.D., 1977). His dissertation became the basis of the book The Merovingian Coinage of the Region of Metz (1982), research on which began as a student in the ANS Summer Graduate Seminar (1975). Much of his scholarly work during his time at ANS was concerned with coinage of the mint of medieval Venice, which resulted in the monographs The Venetian Tornesello: A Medieval Colonial Coinage (1985) and Zecca: The Mint of Venice in the Middle Ages (2000), along with numerous articles. Stahl also took in active role in matters pertaining to medals, serving as editor for two volumes of The Medal in America (1988, 1999), as a U.S.A delegate (1987-2000) and executive committee member (1989-2000) of the Fédération Internationale de la Médaille (FIDEM), and as president (1984-1988) and board member (since 1995) of the American Medallic Sculpture Association (AMSA). In addition to his curatorial duties at ANS, Stahl also was responsible for coordinating the selection of recipients for the Society’s J. Sanford Saltus Medal Award and helped to relaunch the Society’s moribund medallic program in the mid-1980s. After leaving ANS, he has served as a visiting professor at the University of Michigan (2000-2001), Rice University (2001-2002), and the University of Notre Dame (2002), and since 2004 he has been curator of numismatics at Princeton University.
  Contains correspondence, conference materials, professional organization mailings, texts of articles and scholarly papers under review, research notes, and records relating to ANS collections, loans, and exhibits. Correspondence includes scholarly discussions among colleagues and the coordination and review of articles for publication, sometimes with the inclusion of photographs of materials under discussion. There are also replies to inquiries from the general public, the importance of which Stahl stressed in a memorandum (May 18, 1993) to staff. This and additional staff memorandums regarding curatorial policies and procedures can be found in the files “Curatorial Memos” and “General Memos.” Also included are correspondence, notes, and other materials relating to his research on Venetian torneselli (1982-1991); letters to students and former students of the ANS Graduate Summer Seminar, including review notes on their papers; submissions, including artwork and photographs, for several medal design competitions, such as the Statue of Liberty (1985-1987), the quincentenary of Columbus’s voyage (1988-1992), the ANS Endowment (1988-1989), and the ANS 125th anniversary (1982-1983), the last of which includes the original artwork submitted by the winning sculptor, Marcel Jovine. In addition there are materials concerning the Saltus Medal Award Committee (1983-2000); exhibits and other special projects relating to ANS collections, including photographs and other items in files on Indian Peace Medals and the J.P. Morgan collection (both of which contain some of the earliest dated items in the records, ca. 1917-1940s), and materials relating to Victor David Brenner, including biographical items, a deed of gift for a Lincoln plaster by him, and material for an article (1986-1988) and an exhibit (1995). Other topics covered include ANS thefts; materials held on temporary loan at ANS as well as the Society’s loans to other organization; the use of computers for collection control; and newsletters and conference materials of various professional organizations, such as the Fédération Internationale de la Médaille (FIDEM) and the American Medallic Sculpture Association (AMSA). The earliest item in the records is a postcard from a "J.S.S." to Bauman Belden (1914) filed with FIDEM materials (1996-2000).
- Series 15: Carmen Arnold-Biucchi curator correspondence, 1982-1999; 2 cubic feet (2 boxes)
  Arnold-Biucchi, Carmen; Correspondence
  Carmen Arnold-Biucchi joined the ANS staff as a Greek and Roman curatorial assistant in 1982 before becoming assistant curator of ancient coins (1984-1989) and the first Margaret Thompson Curator of Greek Coins (1989-2000). A graduate of the University of Fribourg (M.A., 1971; Ph.D., 1976), she was employed by the Lexicon Iconographicum Mythologiae Classicae (LIMC) in Basle (1974-1977) and at Rutgers University in New Jersey (1979-1981) before her employment at ANS, which followed her attendance of the ANS Graduate Summer Seminar in 1981. She currently holds the position of Damarete Curator of Ancient Coins, Division of Asian and Mediterranean Art, Harvard Art Museums.
- Series 16: Rose Chan Houston curator correspondence, 1947-1988; 0.5 cubic feet (1 box)
  Houston, Rose Chan; Wang, Yu-ch'uan; Correspondence; Reports
  Rose Chan Houston of Bronxville, N.Y., obtained her B.A. from Marion College, Indianapolis, in 1959, before attending Fordham University, obtaining an M.A. in Modern European and American History in 1961 and a Ph.D. in Modern Diplomatic History in 1971. She joined the ANS in 1971 where she served as assistant (1971-1973) and associate (1973-1988) curator of Far Eastern coins. In the summer of 1988 the Far Eastern curatorship was eliminated because of financial constraints. Prior to her time at ANS, Chan had been a librarian at Fordham University (1961-1966) and an instructor of history at Yeshiva University (1968-1969). In later years she again worked as a librarian at the School of the Holy Child in Rye, New York. Her articles on Chinese coins and other topics appeared in such publications as Museum Notes and International Bank Note Society Journal.
- Series 17: William L. Bischoff curator correspondence, 1987; 0.5 cubic feet (1 box)
  Bischoff, William L. (William Ludwig), 1938-; Correspondence
  William L. Bischoff (1938-2010) was assistant (January 1987-October 1988) and associate (October 1988-May 1989) curator of modern coins at the American Numismatic Society. He was born in Dallas, Texas, and grew up in Fresno, California. He attended Stanford (B.A., 1960) and Harvard (Ph.D., 1970) Universities and then went on to hold an assistant professorship at the Universidad de las Americas in Puebla, Mexico (1970-1972), work as director of a prison education program for the Law Enforcement Assistance Administration and the University of Massachusetts in Boston (1973-1974), and teach as an associate professor of Bard College at Simon’s Rock in Great Barrington, Massachusetts. After leaving the ANS, he became curator of numismatics at the Newark Museum (1991-1997).
  Correspondence having to do with inquiries from the general public regarding the hobby of coin collecting and the value and identification of coins, among other topics.
    nnan0115/c_72e210726f13dd83e795409f0b4075dd
  - Inquiries, January 1987
  - Inquiries, February 1987
  - Inquiries, March 1987
  - Inquiries, April 1987
  - Inquiries, May 1987
  - Inquiries, June 1987
  - Inquiries, July 1987
  - Inquiries, August 1987
  - Inquiries, September 1987
  - Inquiries, October 1987
  - Inquiries, November 1987
  - Inquiries, December 1987
- Series 18: William E. Metcalf curator correspondence, 1954-2000, bulk 1982-2000; 10 cubic feet (10 boxes)
  Though some patterns can be discerned, the materials are unarranged. This disorder may have been the result of the packing and unpacking of the records during one of the Society’s physical relocations that took place after Metcalf’s departure.
  Metcalf, William E., 1947-; Correspondence; Memorandums
  William E. Metcalf (b. 1947) served the American Numismatic Society as assistant (1973-1975), associate (1975-1978), and curator (1978-2000) of Roman and Byzantine coins. In addition, he held the positions of deputy chief curator (1978 -1979) and chief curator (1979-2000). Majoring in classical studies, he received his bachelor’s (1969), master’s (1970), and doctorate degrees (1973) at the University of Michigan. After leaving the ANS, Metcalf became an associate professor at New York University (2000-2002) and then professor of classics and curator of coins and medals at Yale University Art Gallery (2002-).